Guide to the North West Company Voyageur Contracts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
North West Company voyageur contracts
1801-1821
WA MSS S-3238
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
1 box
Forty-four printed contracts completed in manuscript, 1801-1821, between North West Company shareholding firms and voyageurs or laborers. Outfitters and destinations include: M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co., to Grand Portage, Rainy Lake, and Timiskaming, 1801 and 1806; Parker, Gerrard, Ogilvy & Co., to Michilimackinac, 18027; Alexander Mackenzie & Co., to Grand Portage and Rainy Lake, 1802; and M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co., to Fort William, 1808-1821.
North West Company
Arrangement
Arranged in chronological order.
North West Company
The North West Company, a Canadian fur trading firms based in Montréal, Québec, was founded in the 1770s and merged with the Hudson's Bay Company in 1821. The Company was comprised of shareholding firms who engaged and outfitted voyageurs to transport furs from trading posts in the Canadian Northwest to Montréal.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2011.
Scope and Contents
Forty-four printed contracts completed in manuscript, 1801-1821, between North West Company shareholding firms and voyageurs or laborers. Outfitters and destinations include: M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co., to Grand Portage, Rainy Lake, and Timiskaming, 1801 and 1806; Parker, Gerrard, Ogilvy & Co., to Michilimackinac, 18027; Alexander Mackenzie & Co., to Grand Portage and Rainy Lake, 1802; and M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co., to Fort William, 1808-1821.
Other Finding Aids
Accompanied by vendor descriptions.
Related Materials
Associated material: Davies/Scroggie collection of Canadian fur trade documents (WA MSS S-2357), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Businessmen -- Québec -- Montréal; Fur trade -- Northwest, Canadian; Fur trade -- Québec -- Montréal; Fur traders -- Northwest, Canadian; Fur traders -- Québec -- Montréal; Thunder Bay (Ont.) -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Grand Portage (Minn.) -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Mackinac County (Mich.) -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Northwest, Canadian -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Rainy Lake (Minn. and Ont.) -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Timiskaming (Ont.) -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Contracts -- Québec -- Montréal -- 19th century; Businessmen -- Québec -- Montréal -- 19th century; Fur traders -- Québec -- Montréal -- 19th century; Alexander Mackenzie & Co; M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co; M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co; North West Company; Parker, Gerrard, Ogilvy & Co
- Voyageur contracts, 1801-1821; Series I
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Jean Marie Boucher, agent, 1801 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Voyageur: Joseph Derosier, dit Lafreniere, of Isle au Castor
    Place: [Montreal]
    Destination: Grand Portage
    Position: devant
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Jean Marie Boucher, agent, 1801 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Voyageur: Jean Baptiste Généreun, of Berthier
    Destination: Rainy Lake
    Position: milieu
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Joseph Faniant, agent, 1801 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Voyageur: Joseph Ossant, dit Lange, of Sorel
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Jean Marie Boucher, agent, 1801 January 28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Voyageur: Joseph de Lorme, of St. Cuthbert
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Voyageur: Antoine Saint Pierre, of Masquinongé
    Destination: Northern posts
    Position: wintering milieu
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Voyageur: Augustin Landry, of Masquinongé
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Voyageur: Pierre Doucett, of Masquinongé
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Voyageur: Jacques Goulet, of Rivière-du-Loup
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Voyageur: Antoine Branchaux, of Rivière-du-Loup
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Voyageur: François Morais, of Rivierre du Louys
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Voyageur: Louis Brulée, of Rivière-du-Loup
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Voyageur: Alexandre Turner, of Rivière-du-Loup
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Voyageur: Michel Boucher, of Rivière-du-Loup, chez Joseph Duaime
    Position: second dans le grande rivierre; gouvernail dans le nord
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Voyageur: François Laurent, of Rivière-du-Loup
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Voyageur: François Bergeron, of Rivière-du-Loup
    Position: second
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Voyageur: Pierre Gabory, of Masquinongé
  - M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.; Louis Belair and Jean Marie Boucher, agents, 1801 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Voyageur: Alexis Ricard, of Rivière-du-Loup
  - Parker, Gerrard, Ogilvy & Co., 1802 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Voyageur: Louis Leblond, of Paroise de St. Anne
    Destination: Michilimackinac
  - Alexander Mackenzie & Co., 1802 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Voyageur: Baptiste Lemarche, of Paroisse de l'Assomption, chez Bat. Blanchard, voisin de Martel
  - Parker, Gerrard, Ogilvy & Co., 1802 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Voyageur: Amable Duplissi, of Paroisse de St. Roch
    Destination:Michilimackinac
  - Alexander Mackenzie & Co., 1802 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Voyageur: François Normandin, of Paroisse de St. Ours
  - Alexander Mackenzie & Co., 1802 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Voyageur: Paul Loinier, of Paroisse de St. Roc
    Position: gouvernail
  - John Gregory, William M'Gillivray, Duncan M'Gillivray, William Hallowell & Roderick M'Kenzie … sous le nom M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; John Gregory, agent, 1806 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - John Gregory, William M'Gillivray, Duncan M'Gillivray, William Hallowell & Roderick M'Kenzie … sous le nom M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; John Gregory, agent, 1806 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Voyageur: Joseph Atien, of Vaudrieul
    Destination: Timiskaming
  - John Gregory, William M'Gillivray, Duncan M'Gillivray, William Hallowell & Roderick M'Kenzie … sous le nom M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; John Gregory, agent, 1806 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Voyageur: Joseph Lariviere, of Cedres
  - John Gregory, William M'Gillivray, Duncan M'Gillivray, William Hallowell & Roderick M'Kenzie … sous le nom M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; John Gregory, agent, 1806 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Voyageur: Charles Dechamps, of Vaudreuil
  - Parker, Gerrard, Ogilvy & Co., 1807 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Voyageur: Jean Marie Acheté, of "en ville"
    Destination: Bay of Quinte
    Position: journalier
  - William Larue, 1807 August 10 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Voyageur: Antoine Mineron, of St. Rose
    Destination: Yonge, haut Canada
  - William M'Gillivray, Duncan M'Gillivray, William Hallowell & Roderick M'Kenzie … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain, 1808 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Voyageur: Joseph Barry, of Rivière-du-Loup
    Destination: Department de St. Maurice
    Position: winterer
  - Joseph Forsyth and T. A. Turner, 1808 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Voyageur: Jean Baptiste Brunelle, of "la ville"
    Destination: Kingston
  - Joseph Forsyth and T. A. Turner, 1808 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Voyageur: Jean Baptiste Russell, of Fauxbourg, Québec
  - William M'Gillivray, William Hallowell, Roderick M'Kenzie, Angus Shaw, Archibald Norman M'Leod et James Hallowell … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; Archibald Norman M'Leod, agent, 1811 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Voyageur: Joseph Pettelle, of Laprairie
    Destination: Fort William
  - William M'Gillivray, William Hallowell, Roderick M'Kenzie, Angus Shaw, Archibald Norman M'Leod et James Hallowell … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; Archibald Norman M'Leod, agent, 1811 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Voyageur: Pierre Trempe, of Masquinongé
  - William M'Gillivray, William Hallowell, Roderick M'Kenzie, Angus Shaw, Archibald Norman M'Leod et James Hallowell … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; Archibald Norman M'Leod, agent, 1811 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Voyageur: François Ladouceur, of St. Menoit
  - William M'Gillivray, William Hallowell, Roderick M'Kenzie, Angus Shaw, Archibald Norman M'Leod et James Hallowell … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; Archibald Norman M'Leod, agent, 1811 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Voyageur: Charles L'Epine, dit Merard, of Grand St. Esprit
    Destination: dépendances du Nord-Ouest
  - William M'Gillivray, William Hallowell, Roderick M'Kenzie, Angus Shaw, Archibald Norman M'Leod et James Hallowell … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; Archibald Norman M'Leod, agent, 1811 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Voyageur: François Paradis, of Sorel
  - William M'Gillivray, William Hallowell, Roderick M'Kenzie, Angus Shaw, Archibald Norman M'Leod et James Hallowell … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; Archibald Norman M'Leod, agent, 1811 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Voyageur: Joseph Potvin, of Maska
  - William M'Gillivray, William Hallowell, Roderick M'Kenzie, Angus Shaw, Archibald Norman M'Leod et James Hallowell … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; Archibald Norman M'Leod, agent, 1811 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Voyageur: Jean Baptiste Dechamp, of Vaudreuil
  - William M'Gillivray, William Hallowell, Roderick M'Kenzie, Angus Shaw, Archibald Norman M'Leod et James Hallowell … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; Archibald Norman M'Leod, agent, 1811 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Voyageur: Pierre Malette, of Rigaut Rivière à la Graisse
  - William M'Gillivray, William Hallowell, Roderick M'Kenzie, Angus Shaw, Archibald Norman M'Leod et James Hallowell … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. et John Ogilvy et Thomas Thain; Angus Shaw, agent, 1811 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Voyageur: Elias Bourdeaux, of Laprairie St. Constant
  - William W. Matthews, 1818 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Voyageur: Joseph La Chapell, of St. Rocque, a present dans les Fauxbourg de Québec
    Destination: winterer, three years
  - William M'Gillivray, Simon M'Gillivray, Archibald Norman M'Leod, Thomas Thain, et Henry Mackenzie … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. & Pierre de Rocheblave; Archibald Norman M'Leod, agent, 1820 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Voyageur: Etienne Ducharme, dit Charron, of Berthier, and Georges Derie, of Masquinongé
  - William M'Gillivray, Simon M'Gillivray, Archibald Norman M'Leod, Thomas Thain, et Henry Mackenzie … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. & Pierre de Rocheblave; Archibald Norman M'Leod, agent, 1820 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Voyageur: Leger Robin, of Sorel
  - William M'Gillivray, Simon M'Gillivray, Archibald Norman M'Leod, Thomas Thain, et Henry Mackenzie … sous le nom M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co. & Pierre de Rocheblave; Archibald Norman M'Leod, agent, 1821 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Voyageur: Jean Baptiste Tousignant, of Masquinongé